<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes concernynge the general cou[n]cell, holden at Trydent by the emperoure and the Germaynes wyth all the nobles of Hungarye, Constantinople and Rome Translated out of Germayne into Englysh by Jhon Holibush. Anno 1548.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843783</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13956)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 635:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes concernynge the general cou[n]cell, holden at Trydent by the emperoure and the Germaynes wyth all the nobles of Hungarye, Constantinople and Rome Translated out of Germayne into Englysh by Jhon Holibush. Anno 1548.</title>
                  <author>Hollybush, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynt Andrewes paryshe in the ware dropt, by Thomas Raynalde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted t Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1549?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>End of text dated from Augsburg, 6 December 1548.</note>
                  <note>"A letter to a friend concerning both the matters taken up at the Dict of Augsburg and matters of diplomacy".--NUC Pre-1956 Catalog.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹⁰.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Council of Trent (1545-1563) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8539:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8539:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Newes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge the general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell / holden at Trydent by the Emperoure and the Germaynes wyth all the nobles of Hungarye / Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenople and Rome Tranſlated oute of Germayne into Englyſh By Ihon Holibuſh.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1548,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Priuilegio ad Imprimendum Solum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8539:2"/>
            <p>After dew ſalutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me to you truſty fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, letti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you were, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where in my laſt wrytinge to you I wrote, that (by the leaue of the bountefull grace and licence of the Imperiall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye) I wolde ſhortelye be wyth you, wherfore at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme I wrote no neweltyes to you concerning this Imperiall parlament. But for as muche as thys purpoſe of myne is hyndred, &amp; I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to tary here vntyll the retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhypful in god father the Cardinal &amp; byſhop of Tride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which is ſent to Rome with a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy meſſage, I wolde not leaue to certify you of ſome newes, ſo far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as I may do &amp; becommeth me.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt as concerninge the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles propoſed of the Imperiall maieſty to the eſtates of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre,
<pb facs="tcp:8539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I truſt year fully certifyed And though the anſwere vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deferred, &amp; ſpecially that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet at the length, by the grace of god, haue the States wyth one conſente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed and requyred, that the ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance concernynge the Religion that is in controuerſye vndeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, maye be determined in the generall, fre and chriſten con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell that alredy is poynted, bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and continueth at Tride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The whych requeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Imperours ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye hath alſo thought yt mooſt conuenient, chriſten and ſure way to alaye all debate and controuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye: ſpecially for as moche as the ſytuacyon of Germanye is not greatly onmete for the purpoſe, nether can other nacions greatly grudge at the waye and diſtance
<pb facs="tcp:8539:3"/>
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Trident, wherby they myght pretende incommodite wher vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Emperiall maieſtye truſteth that euery and ſyngular eſtate of the Empyre wyll agre to ſuche a generall councel, ſubmytting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humbly to it, acceptyng &amp; redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſame: In doynge of whyche, they ſhall folowe the footeſteppes of the auncient fathers, which haue alwayes in doubtes of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or fayth, hadde theyr recourſe to the councel as vnto a ſentuary, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed them wyllingly after the ordinance of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And that ſuch a fre general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell haue the better progreſſe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuance, &amp; that noman nedeth to feare interruption of it or hynde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce: the Emperours maieſtye as a maynteiner of the churche,
<pb facs="tcp:8539:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and defendour of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell wyl godly helpe and buſyly prouyde, that ſuch a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell begon at Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent haue hys quick courſe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. He wylleth alſo that it be viſited augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; confirmed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of other chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces &amp; nations, ſpecially Archbyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Biſhops &amp; other Prelates of Germany (as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are &amp; haue ben chefe aucthors or makers of thys debate,) or in theyr lawfull abſence, by theyr wyſe, learned &amp; fully aucthoriſed deputyes.</p>
            <p>It ſhalbe lawful alſo for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the Auſboroweſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion ſafe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duted to come to remayne &amp; returne agayn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, &amp; ther ſhalbe grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dew au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience. By theſe meanes ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole treating of this general co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be godly
<pb facs="tcp:8539:4"/>
and Chriſtenly (all affections and parcialite ſet a parte) accordynge to the doctryne of holye ſcripture and holy fathers, whereof maye folowe a chriſten reformation, by the whych peruerſe doctryne and abuſes maye be rooted out.</p>
            <p>As for the pleatynges of the Imperiall chamber or hall, wyll the Imperiall maieſty continent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye reforme, and that wyth conue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nient Iudges, Preſydentes and Extraordinare perſons, that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice maye be comly executed, and ther to be no more lackes.</p>
            <p>Ther are alſo other cauſes han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deled in thys parlament Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as are of peace, of the Coine and ſuche lyke, which are come to ſuche a pointe, as is to be hoped no man can haue a iuſt cauſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8539:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>We do hope alſo that this Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>periall parlamente ſhalbe ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ended, whych myght be whan the worſhypfull Cardynall and Byſhoppe of Trident ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, who departed hence oute of Auſborowe the ſyxte daye of Nouember beynge ſent to Rome vnto the Byſhoppe of Rome, for the continuaunce of the Counſell of Trident, and to approue or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the reformation, how euery man ſhal be haue hymſelf, during the tyme of the generall counſell. The whyche came to Rome the eyghtenth day of Nouember, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence he hath wrytten: he wylbe ſhortelye wythe vs agayne, and bryng wyth hym al thynges that haue ben the requeſtes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riall maieſty, and the States.</p>
            <p>Nother can I wytholde to cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyfye
<pb facs="tcp:8539:5"/>
you / that the maieſtye of the kyng of rome Ferdina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus ſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt yere an embaſſadour / named Lord Gerarde Veltwick to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople to the greate Turke / for to demaunde truce for .v. yere the whych requeſt the Turke dyd eaſely graunt / partly for drede of the Emperiall maieſtye / whome he nameth a vanquyſher / &amp; Lord of Europa / partly becauſe of the Aſſaultes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Soldane or kinge of Perſes / whych combreth hym wyth warres: but vpon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion: yf the Imperiall maieſty wyll holde / conſent &amp; agre to the ſame truce. The Romane kinges Embaſſador lord Veltwick hath agreed to that condityon / &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed to buſye hymſelfe to cauſe the Imperiall maieſtye conſente to thys truce: doutynge not / but
<pb facs="tcp:8539:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
truſting, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperial maieſty wold not refuſe it for the tender loue he oweth to his brother. And vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayde lord Veltwick come hether wyth the Turkes meſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, deſyringe to know, whether the Emperiall maieſty wyll agree to this truce of fyue yeres, or not: that theſe forſayde meſſangers of the Turke, may bringe theyr lord an anſwer. Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whych hath the Emperiall maieſtye anſwered on this wyſe: Though it becommeth not our maieſtye, to make any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the enemy of oure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nother hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Godly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty euer left vs aydeleſſe hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to but alway proſpereth &amp; helpeth vs to vanquyſh our enemyes: ſo that noman ther is, whych can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce and ſay: I haue ouercome Charles in battayll. For ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:8539:6"/>
alſo as almyghtye God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued vs wyth ſo greate puyſſance ryches, men of warre &amp; captaynes ſo that we nede not to be afrayed of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world: yet for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der loue that we owe to our bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the king of the romanes, Ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gary &amp; Bemes we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, alow &amp; ratifye the truce of fyue yeares but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyſh Emperour do ſende vs hys letters &amp; ſpecificayo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerning this peace. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Turkyſhe meſſaungers had receaued thys coragious anſwere of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall maieſtye, they are returned to theyr Lorde, which continently ſente ouer the foreſayde letters, in the whyche he calleth the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours maieſty a Lord of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten worlde. Theſe letters came here to Auſborowe the .xxi. day of
<pb facs="tcp:8539:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Nouember, whyche I haue both handeled and ſene. Theſe be wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten wyth greate and vnſemely let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, and on the top ſygned wyth the great Turkes armes of gold. I doubte whether I euer haue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne any ſuche lyke, they be nother Chalde nor Hebrue letters, the Lord Gerard veltwick ſayth they be Arabyck letters.</p>
            <p>Ther is alſo tydynges come oute of Hungary that a Lorde of the Kynges counſell, called loce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tz whych fauoured more the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyſhe partye than hys own lyege Lordes, nether hearde gladly the truce made: for his enterpryſes in manye poyntes were hyndered.</p>
            <p>This ſame as he ſat vpon a tyme at hys table, and hys ſeruauntes about hym, one of them began ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly to crye: Come death &amp; haue
<pb facs="tcp:8539:7"/>
me awaye. And ſodenlye he caſte an horrible ſyght wyth turnynge of hys eyes, raygynge and crying hugly with a loud voyce: The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll is in me, and hath poſſeſſed me, nother wyll he leaue wyth me, but more of you muſt daunce this daunce. The other ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes wold haue bounde hym, but he ſpewed frome hym, and behaued hym ſo woodlye: afterward caſt he out at hys mouth the ſtomack, bowele, lyuer, harte, and all hys entrayles by peces. After that bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other of the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to rage and waxe woode, cryenge &amp; howlynge pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly &amp; hugly: I am poſſeſſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl. The ſame dyd they binde, &amp; Lozentz ſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly for his par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon to coniure the euyl ſpryt. But before the prieſt came, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to rage alſo, which was
<pb facs="tcp:8539:7"/>
bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de as the other. With y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lozentz to be greatly a frayed: &amp; though the prieſt prayed moch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hym, yet bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he to rage lyke the other &amp; crye, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he alſo was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrayned to be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And lay of this wyſe in his houſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his two ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes (for the fyrſt dyed) xiiii. dayes before. In the meane why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſwaged the woodneſt, &amp; he was lowſed of his ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: but hys cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te is yet ſo horrible &amp; drede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare approche hym.</p>
            <p>Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foreſayde truces were in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / a ſhyp was ſpoyled vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our borders &amp; ſoncked which paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in valure .xx.M. gold gylde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and al they that were in her were drowned: but the dede doers are yet vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether thei be chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Turkes that ioyne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the borders. Cattia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s brother in lawe
<pb facs="tcp:8539:8"/>
hath ſlayne two hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth Turkes that paſſed the borders, and inua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded oure men, wherwyth he hath apeaced &amp; ſtylled the other. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe tydynges came here to Auſbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the .xix. daye of Nouember, but ther was no credence geuen to them, vntyl ther came more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer certificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Kynges Maieſtye and other Lordes.</p>
            <p>The .xxvi. daye of Nouember laſt paſt came hether thre wedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, namelye my lady Mary que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of Hungary and Regente, the Ducheſſe of Loren, and the ladye Princeſſe of Orenge of Brabant: whome met the Kynges grace of Rome, the Archduke of Auſtriche hys ſonne, and the electours, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melye of Colens Saxonye and Braundeborowe, be ſyde a greate nombre of Byſhops, Dukes, and
<pb facs="tcp:8539:8"/>
Lords, ſo that they entred at Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow ſyxe hundreth on horſebak</p>
            <p>They of Auſborow alſo haue made peace wyth theyr Lorde the Byſhop, whereof the condicions be, that for the force, ſpoyling and iniuries they haue done him, ſhal in recompence therof geue him fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue &amp; nyntye thouſande golde gyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and for the ſpiritual rentes that they haue receaued thyrtye thouſande golde gyldens.</p>
            <p>Ther is here ſuch a nombre of Lordes and Princes / as neuer hath ben ſene in any parlamente imperiall.</p>
            <p>The mooſt worſhypfull in god father and Lord Adolyſhe arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhoppe of Colen &amp; hath yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye whych was Saynte Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las euen receaued of the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all maieſtye hys dignitye.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8539:9"/>Muche were to be wrytten of the takyng of the Duke of Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony elector was, and the Landt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, but the ſhorteneſſe of thys letter, and alſo the tyme wyll not admytte it. Yet can not I wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olde you that Landtgraues wyfe with her chyldren, haue delyuered a'great byll or ſupplication to the States of the Empyre, wherein they ſygnified, that thoſe articles whych were delyuered at the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the Landtgraue, were ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fylled, expyred and accomplyſhed: requyred al the States of the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyre to make ſute for the Landt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue to the Emperyall maieſtye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght be delyuered. Some of the Princes gaue conſent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but ſome toke deliberation vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon it. In the meane whyle as thys was in hande: was the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb facs="tcp:8539:9"/>
Maieſtye aduertyſed of thys. And whan the Princes we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nowe conſultynge and takyng theyr aduyſe, dyd the Emperiall maieſtye ſende them a farre other certyfycation of the matter, than that of the La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dtgraue ſpecyfye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the cauſes why it were not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diente, nether for the commune peace, nor the contry, that he ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be releaſed and ſet at liberte.</p>
            <p>It declared alſo playnly, that the articles of the Landtgraue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſion or yeldyng, were not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed aryghte nor lawfullye: yea were not executed nother of the Landtgraue. The Emperoures maieſtye alſo anſwered ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and wyth ſo manyfeſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratyons to theſe thynges that were propoſed the Princes by the Landtgraue, that they all ceaſed of
<pb facs="tcp:8539:10"/>
makynge ſute for hym, but were of a contrarye mynde. Wherfore he was remoued from donwerte, to Norlinges, wyth duble warde whych thynge doth greatly greue and diſpleaſe hym, complaynyng bewayling and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng to be ſo remoued from place to place.</p>
            <p>Duke noritz of Saxony elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is departed from hence nowe of late, of whome the fame goeth, that he is gone to take vp men of warre in the name of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours maieſtye, the truth wherof, I cannot wryte for a certaynte.</p>
            <p>Thys is of a truth, that here are many doughty captaynes, &amp; that moche artillery is ſent towarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coſtes to Switcherland. They of Berne are afrayed, and haue ofte ſent to the Duke of Sauoye, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyrynge to haue peace with him
<pb facs="tcp:8539:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
What ende theſe matters ſhal ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue, can I not ſhew at this tyme.</p>
            <p>I truſt your gentlyneſſe wyll take thys wrytynge in worth, as I ſhall come by you, (the which I truſt ſhalbe ſhortely) I ſhall ſhew you more newes by mouth Fare well</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶Wryten from Auguſt <date>the ſyxt daye of December. The yeare of oure Lorde. M.D.Xlviii</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſaynt Andrewes paryſhe in the ware dropt, by Thomas Raynalde.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
